Guide to the Southerners on New Ground records, 1993-2015 RL.01231
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Southerners on New Ground records
1993-2015
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Southerners on New Ground
Breedlove, Caitlin
RL.01231
17.3 Linear Feet
According to the organization's website, Southerners on New Ground (SONG) is an intersectional activist organization that works to build, connect, and sustain those in the South who believe in liberation across all lines of race, class, culture, gender and sexuality. It was established in 1994 following a National Lesbian and Gay Task Force meeting. SONG is currently headquartered in Atlanta with regional offices across the South. The accession (2009-0098) (9.6 lin. ft.; dated 1993-2004) includes administrative and financial records, programming materials, and organizational files, all stemming from retreats, training, workshops, and community events sponsored or promoted by SONG. The accession also includes SONG materials from the Bayard Rustin project, People of Color activities, Pride at Work, and the Highlander Economy Educational Institute, among others. The accession (2015-0113) (2.9 lin. ft.; dated 2006-2015) was donated by Caitlin Breedlove, Co-Director of SONG from 2006-2015. It includes administrative and financial records, programming information, flyers and promotional materials and research related to campaign initiatives from her time in the SONG leadership.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
Gift, 2009 (2009-0098), 9.6 lin. ft.; Gift, 2015 (2015-0133), 2.9 lin. ft.
Biographical / Historical Note
Southerners on New Ground (SONG) was established in 1994 following a 1993 National Gay and Lesbian Task Force conference that brought black and white lesbians together in an effort to unite LGBT communities with racial minorities, particularly African Americans, against discrimination by conservative, right-wing groups. SONG attempts to provide a regional infrastructure for LGBT organizing through retreats, training workshops, meetings, and other community outreach programs. The organization is based in Durham, North Carolina, with offices in Atlanta. It currently has a membership of about 600 primarily LGBT people.
Caitlin Breedlove was Co-Director of SONG from 2006-2015. She self-identifies as a white, queer, second-generation American woman of Central European descent. She has lived in the South consistently through adulhood. She is well-known within the LGBTQ community for her work as a leader, strategist, writer, and adcovte for racial and economic justice. During her time at SONG, she led a number of innovative intersectional movement building initiatives in the LGBTQ sector. She advanced numerous SONG campaigns, built new alliances, and trained a larger cohort of organizers. Under her co-leadership, SONG membership grew to over 3,000 individuals. She currently lives in Goldsboro, North Carolina with her partner and daughter.
Collection Overview
The accession (2009-0098) (9.6 lin. ft.; dated 1993-2004) includes administrative and financial records, programming materials, and organizational files, all stemming from retreats, training, workshops, and community events sponsored or promoted by SONG. The accession also includes SONG materials from the Bayard Rustin project, People of Color activities, Pride at Work, and the Highlander Economy Educational Institute, among others. Acquired as part of the Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture.
The accession (2015-0113) (2.9 lin. ft.; dated 2006-2015) was donated by Caitlin Breedlove, Co-Director of SONG from 2006-2015. It includes administrative and financial records, programming information, flyers and promotional materials and research related to campaign initiatives from her time in the SONG leadership. The accession also contains cards and artwork given to Caitlin by others, assorted photographs from events, two interview recordings, and many of her personal notebooks. Acquired as part of the Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture.
Homosexuality -- Southern States; United States -- Social conditions -- 1990-; Discrimination -- Southern States; DVDs; Videotapes; Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture; Southerners on New Ground
- Accession (2009-0098), 1993-2004, 7 boxes
  Scope and Contents note
  The accession (2009-0098) (7200 items; 9.6 lin. ft.; dated 1993-2004) includes administrative and financial records, programming materials, and organizational files, all stemming from retreats, training, workshops, and community events sponsored or promoted by SONG. The accession also includes SONG materials from the Bayard Rustin project, People of Color activities, Pride at Work, and the Highlander Economy Educational Institute, among others. Acquired as part of the Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture.
  Arrangement note
  This is an unprocessed addition to this collection. Materials have not been arranged beyond their original condition, and folder titles may not accurately reflect folder contents. Please consult Research Services if you have any questions.
  - Programs and workshop evaluations, 1996-2001 (Box 1)
    - Pride at Work (Box 1)
    - Dismantling Internalized Homophobia (Box 1)
    - Level Playing Field (Box 1)
    - People of Color (Box 1)
    - Beyond White Guilt (Box 1)
    - Broadening the We (Box 1)
  - Town meetings, 1997 (Box 1)
  - Organizational early work, 1994 (Box 1)
  - Highlander Economic Education Institute (Box 1)
  - Poor People's Movement, 1998 (Box 1)
  - Regional Economic Justice Network (REJN) (Box 1)
  - Organizational files, A-N (Box 1)
  - Workshops (Box 2)
    - Higher Ground, 2000 (Box 2)
    - WomonWrites, 1995 (Box 2)
  - Retreats
    - Atlanta, 1994 (Box 2)
    - Women's Retreat, 2000-2001 (Box 2)
    - Retreat summary logs (Box 2)
    - People of Color Retreat, 1997-1998, 2000 (Box 2)
    - Allies Retreat, 1998 (Box 2)
    - Cultural Worker Retreat, 1996-1999 (Box 2)
  - Mapping Project (Box 2)
  - Printed materials (Box 2)
  - SONG conferences and programs, 2003
    - NC Unity Conference (Box 2)
    - Black Solidarity (Box 2)
    - Durham/NCCU Now (Box 2)
    - Training Conference (Box 2)
    - SC Pride Conference (Box 2)
  - Articles of Incorporation, 1998 (Box 2)
  - Bylaws (Box 2)
  - Membership information (Box 2)
  - Personnel policies (Box 2)
  - Akers, David B. (Box 2)
  - Direct Appeals (Box 2)
  - Southern retreat locations (Box 2)
  - Advertisements (Box 2)
  - Videotapes (2) (Box 2)
  - National Gay and Lesbian Task Force (NGLTF) (Box 3)
    - People of Color (POC) Planning Committee (Box 3)
    - Creating Change, 2000-2001 (Box 3)
  - National Organizers Alliance (NOA), 2001 (Box 3)
  - National Black Gay and Lesbians (NBGL) Forum (Box 3)
  - Organizational files, N-Z (Box 3)
  - South Africa, 1999 (Box 3)
  - Rustin Project
    - Program (Box 3)
    - Applications (Box 3)
    - Retreat (Box 3)
    - Evaluations (Box 3)
    - Durham (Box 3)
    - Atlanta (Box 3)
    - New Orleans (Box 3)
    - Louisville (Box 3)
  - SONG Training curricula materials (Box 4)
  - Bayard Rustin Project materials, 2001 (Box 4)
  - Florida Coalition Against Domestic Violence training materials, 2001 (Box 4)
  - SONG logos (Box 4)
  - Correspondence, 1994-2001 (Box 4)
  - Hate mail (Box 4)
  - Program files, 1993-2001 (Box 4)
  - Printed materials (Box 4)
  - IRS communications, 1999 (Box 4)
  - Emergency Conference and Project South, 2001 (Box 4)
  - Administrative files, 2002
    - Brochures (Box 4)
    - Staff meetings (Box 4)
    - Move information (Box 4)
    - Bulletin board (Box 4)
  - SONG 10th Anniversary, 2004 (Box 4)
  - To Do folders, 2003 (Box 4)
  - Administrative files, 2003 (Box 5)
  - Administrative files, 2000s (Box 6)
  - Fundraising (Box 6)
  - Outreach (Box 6)
  - Bayard Rustin project (Box 6)
  - Organizational development and marketing (Box 6)
  - Samples (Box 6)
  - Videotapes (15) (Box 7)
    - In the Name of Justice Seminar, Tape 1-3, 2004 (Box 7)
    - In the Name of Justice Seminar, Tape 4-7, 2004 (Box 7)
    - Gay Cuba, 1995 (Box 7)
    - A Gay and Lesbian Speak Out (Box 7)
    - From the Mountains to the Maquiladoras (Box 7)
    - SONG Retreat (Box 7)
    - Free Speech TV
      - And Justice For All PSA Intro/Outro Tape (Box 7)
      - And Justice For All Clip Tape (Box 7)
      - And Justice For All sample tapes Nos. 1, 2, 4-7, 9 (Box 7)
  - SONG 15th anniversary DVD (Box 7)
- Accession (2015-0133), 2006-2015; 5 boxes
  Scope and Contents
  The accession (2015-0113) (2.9 lin. ft.; dated 2006-2015) was donated by Caitlin Breedlove, Co-Director of SONG from 2006-2015. It includes administrative and financial records, programming information, flyers and promotional materials and research related to campaign initiatives from her time in the SONG leadership. The accession also contains cards and artwork given to Caitlin by others, assorted photographs from events, two interview recordings, and many of her personal notebooks. Acquired as part of the Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture.
  - Administrative and program files, 2006-2015 (Box 8-9)
  - En Nueva Tierra bandanas, 2012 (Box 10)
  - Mini SONG rainbow flags, 2012 (Box 10)
  - Igniting the Kindred Song handmade shirt, 2012 (Box 10)
  - Painted N.C. SONG banner 57" x 56," undated (Box 10)
  - Wall-mounting post-it notes from gatherings, undated (Box 10)
  - 15th Video and Caitlin Breedlove interview (Box 11)
  - Caitlin Breedlove cards and artwork from others (Box 11)
  - SONG flyers and promotional materials (Box 11)
  - Photographs (Box 11)
  - Publications, 4 folders (Box 11)
  - SONG staff retreat, 2009 (Box 11)
  - SONG staff retreat, 2012 (Box 11)
  - SONG Staff retreat, 2013 (Box 11)
  - SONG staff orientation manual (Box 11)
  - Organizing for Movement Building Toolkit (Box 11)
  - Campaign research team (Box 11)
  - Free From Fear Campaign, 2015 (Box 11)
  - Queer Resiliency (Box 11)
  - Global Exchange Toolkit (Box 11)
  - Amnesty for Prisoners of Katrina Campaign, 2006 (Box 11)
  - Reports from the Field Pre-Writing Worksheet (Box 11)
  - Strong Elements of Multi-Racial Organizations (Box 11)
  - Durham Transgender Day of Remembrance Memorial, 2014 (Box 11)
  - BC Song Campaign (Box 11)
  - Road Opener Awards, 2012 (Box 11)
  - Better Together Leadership Cohort, April 25-26, 2013 (Box 11)
  - SONG Events at University of Virginia, October 20, 2013 (Box 11)
  - Virginia Organizing School, 2012 (Box 11)
  - Arcus Foundation Staff and Community Dialogue (Box 11)
  - Deep Listening Campaign Responses (Box 11)
  - SONG Rural Program (Box 11)
  - Voter Registration N.C. (Box 11)
  - Creating Change, 2015 (Box 11)
  - Out South, 2014; 2 folders (Box 11)
  - Moral Monday, June 2, 2014 (Box 11)
  - Amendment One Meeting and Talking Points (Box 11)
  - Catawba County Protest, May 27, 2012 (Box 11)
  - All of Us Curriculum (Box 11)
  - Signs from N.C. Marriage Win (Box 11)
  - A Call to Action, May 8, 2012 (Box 11)
  - Administrative and Financial Documents, 2008-2015; 9 folders (Box 11)
  - Caitlin Breedlove Notebook, 2014 (Box 11)
  - Caitlin Breedlove Notebooks, 2010-2014; 6 folders (Box 12)
  - Shanice Through the System juvenile justice exercise (Box 13)
  - Mountaintop Festival and Retreat, 1996-1999; 7 folders (Box 13)
  - For Lovers and Fighters by Dean Spade, and Black Theater Festival by August Wilson, 1997-2006 (Box 13)
  - Southern Regional Conference leadership packet, 2008 (Box 13)
  - Administrative materials, 2001 (Box 13)
  - SONG operational information, 2001 (Box 13)
  - SONG organizational information, 2002 (Box 13)
  - Roots of Terror workshop, 2003 (Box 13)
  - National Gay and Lesbian Task Force Conference, 2004 (Box 13)
  - Board Meeting reports, 2005-2006 (Box 13)
  - NC Center for Nonprofits (Box 14)
  - Grants
    - Tides Foundation Grant, 2003 (Box 14)
    - Fund for Southern Communities Grant, 2003 (Box 14)
    - Southern Partners Fund Grant, 2003-2004; 2 folders (Box 14)
    - Gill Foundation Grants, 2003-2005; 2 folders (Box 14)
    - Astrea Foundation Grants, 2003-2006; 3 folders (Box 14)
    - Southern Funding Collaborative Grant, 2005 (Box 14)
    - Grants, 2005 (Box 14)
    - Grant Reports Due, 2006 (Box 14)